INVENTORY OF THE ROBERT VALANAY CORRESPONDENCE, 1921-1978
The Getty Research Institute
Robert Valanay correspondence
1921-1978
950057
Valanay, Robert
3 linear feet (5 boxes)
Getty Research Institute Research Library Special Collections and Visual Resources 1200 Getty Center Drive, Suite 1100 Los Angeles, CA 90049-1688
Collection comprises ca. 1600 letters (ca. 1921-ca. 1978) sent to Robert Valanay, the French poet and critic, from artists and writers of the surrealist group. Twelve letters are from Valanay. The collection includes a translation in manuscript by Valanay, 5 manuscripts by others, printed ephemera, and ca. 50 photographs, most presumably taken by Valanay.
Administrative Information
Access
Open for use by qualified researchers.
Acquisition Information
Acquired 1995.
Biographical/Historical Note
Robert Valanay, born in 1903, was a poet, translator and literary critic who worked with and admired many of the artists and poets of the surrealist group. His literary achievements are all the more remarkable as he held a "day job" with Shell, translating as well as making documentary films for the company for many years.
In the thirties, he seems to have published at least two volumes of poetry Flot et jusant and Oiseau nitre; another collection, Mots deserre-freins which assembled many of the early poems, appeared in 1972. However, Valanay seems to have been most appreciated and sought after for his translations. Indeed, he was considered the official translator of Max Ernst and Hans Arp.
Scope and Content of Collection
Letters to and from Robert Valanay represent the personal and professional correspondence still in Valanay's possession upon his death. They span a period of over 50 years from the 1920s to the 1970s and treat a wide variety of literary issues that likewise concerned much of the French avant-garde. Among the prominent surrealist and Dada artists and poets who figure in this archive are Hans Arp, Hans Bellmer, Andr Breton, Blaise Cendrars, Ren Char, Jean Crotti, Paul Eluard, Max Ernst, Raoul Hausmann, Maurice Heine, Richard Huelsenbeck, Georges Hugnet, Marcel Jean, Guy Lvis, Mano, Pierre de Massot, Amde Ozenfant, Meret Oppenheim, Henri Parisot, Pastoureau, Roland Penrose, Man Ray, Hans Richter, Guy Rosey, Andr Salmon, Yves Tanguy and Jacques Villon.
Valanay's activities can be divided into his poetic efforts and his work as a translator. As a young man, he seems to have been involved with a group of Norman poets whose most famous member was a Charles Thophile Fret. The letters from Fret, Charles Boulen, Fernand Fleuret, Napolon Roinard are concerned with the promotion of Norman literature and they clearly consider Valanay an ally in their campaign. This group of writers also encouraged Valanay's poetic aspirations, congratulating him on the publication of various articles and volumes of poetry. By 1930, Valanay had made the acquaintance of many of the French poets associated with surrealism. The collection includes letters from Andr Breton, Blaise Cendrars, Ren Char, Paul Eluard and Georges Hugnet. Valanay was a close friend--they use the "tu" form of address--of both Eluard and Hugnet; the Hugnet letters are particularly warm and express the anxiety of living in war-time Paris.
Valanay's interest in translation may have been ignited by his German teacher Maurice Boucher who was himself a poet and translator. In the more than 60 letters that Boucher sent Valanay, we witness the development of his career. The correspondence begins as a mentor relationship with Boucher offering encouragement and criticism--sometimes extremely technical--of Valanay's poetic efforts and then, over time, changes into a cordial collegiality. As their translator, Valanay was a close friend of Hans Arp, Max Ernst and Hans Bellmer and received a good deal of correspondence from all three men. The Bellmer letters detail a very difficult period, the war years, in the life of their author, offering a vivid autobiographical account of Bellmer's struggle to continue his artistic pursuits despite circumstances. The Ernst and Arp letters concern more professional issues that occupied artist and translator alike.
Valanay received some 70 letters from Henri Parisot who edited L'Age d'or and was associated with the publications Fontaine, Les Quatre Vents and Les Cahiers du sud. Parisot solicited Valanay's help in preparing a volume of German poems translated into French, entitled Anthologie de la posie humoristique. The collection also includes Valanay's manuscript translations, presumably for this volume, of poems by Paul Celan, Heissenbttel, Erich Fried, Wilhelm Busch, Christian Morgenstern and Joachim Ringelnatz.
Apart from the aforementioned correspondence, there are interesting letters from other artists, critics and editors associated with surrealism such as Marcel Jean, Francis Picabia, Raoul Hausmann, Maurice Heine, Guy Lvis, Pierre de Massot, Ozenfant, Meret Oppenheim, Pastoureau, Yves Poupard-Lieussou, Raymond Queneau, Man Ray, Hans Richter, Guy Rosey, Yves Tanguy and Jacques Villon. The Valanay letters also include a significant number of lesser known critics, editors and translators that, from a social historian's point of view, potentially offer a valuable source for the reconstruction of this artistic and cultural milieu.
The Valanay letters also contain about 50 photographs; most were presumably taken by Valanay. There are three pornographic postcards which may have come from Paul Eluard's infamous collection. Finally, some 50 letters and cards, despite the best efforts of the cataloguer, remain unidentified.
The papers are organized in 2 series: Series I. Letters received, 1921-1978; Series II. Manuscripts and photographs, 1932-1978.
Indexing terms
Subjects
Valanay, Robert; Surrealism
Form/Genre
Correspondence; Ephemera; Photographic prints; Photographs, Original
Contributors
Arp, Jean, 1887-1966; Bellmer, Hans, 1902-1975; Breton, Andr, 1896-1966; Eluard, Paul, 1895-1952; Ernst, Max, 1891-1976; Hausmann, Raoul, 1886-1971; Huelsenbeck, Richard, 1892-1974; Hugnet, Georges, 1906-1974; Massot, Pierre de; Oppenheim, Meret, 1913-; Ozenfant, Amde, 1886-1966; Parisot, Henri; Poupard-Lieussou, Yves; Ray, Man, 1890-1976; Richter, Hans, 1888-1976; Tanguy, Yves, 1900-1955; Villon, Jacques, 1875-1963
Container List
- Letters received, 1921-1978, Series I.; ca. 1600 items
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent, some of the letters are accompanied by ephemera. Twelve letters from Valanay are included.
  - Acker, Adolphe, 11 Aug 1970-9 Aug 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    3 handwritten letters.
  - Adma, Marcel, 7 Oct 1946-7 Oct 1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    2 handwritten letters.
  - Aegertes, E., 23 Oct 1929-7 Apr 1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aeramov, Georges (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Russian postcard.
  - Albessard, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Altmann, Robert, 22 Apr 1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    typed letter.
  - Apollinaire, Jacqueline, undated, ca. 1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    5 handwritten letters, 2 autograph cards signed, 1 carte de visite signed. All are undated but from contents an approximate date of 1928 can be deduced. She discusses plans for constructing a monument to her late husband and supplies bio-bibliographical information for an edition of Guillaume Apollinaire's work.
  - Arp, Hans, 1 Apr 1946-23 Oct 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    18 typed letters, 13 postcards signed and 7 telegrams. The letters mostly concern arranging eventual rendez-vous or rescheduling them. Arp also discusses briefly his activities such as working on a book, articles and mentions that he attended the opening of a Magnelli exhibition. The postcards are frequently witty and some have little collages by Arp.Joined: Typescript of "Danger de Mort" dated 1953, an original lithograph by Arp made as a New Year's card and signed by Marguerite and Hans, 5 invitations to Arp's exhibitions from 1946-1966, some newspaper clippings and an article by Marguerite Arp, "Arp as I knew him," read at the Guggenheim Museum in May 1969.
  - Arp-Hagenbach, Marquerite, 23 May 1946-11 Aug 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    18 handwritten letters, 15 typed letters, 1 letter written by Suzanne Feigel and signed by M. Arp, 24 postcards signed. Marguerite acts as a kind of secretary for Arp, often writing in his place, "Arp me charge de..." It seems that Arp and Valanay are in close collaboration, Valanay translating many of Arp's texts into French while Marguerite coordinates their efforts. However, in 1951, Marguerite is at work on her own translation and asks Valanay for advice. Both she and Arp appreciate Valanay's translation of Auguste Bolte with engravings by Ernst. After Arp's death in 1966, Marguerite continues the correspondence with Valanay, discussing Arp's legacy as well as her own health problems.
    Joined: The wedding announcement of Hans Arp and Marguerite Hagenbach's marriage and an invitation to Marguerite's 80th birthday party.
  - Arp, Franois, 5 Apr 1962-18 Jun 1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    2 handwritten letters, a typed letter and a carte de visite. Because of Marguerite's illness, Franois Arp takes charge of his brother's correspondence.
  - Arts Council of Great Britain, 17 Aug 1977-28 Apr 1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    9 typed letters by Roland Penrose (1), Joanna Drew (2), and Richard Francis (6). All concern loans by Valanay for the exhibition "Dada and Surrealism" in the Hayward Gallery London.
  - Aubier, Fernand, 19 Jun 1941-28 May 1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Balascheff, Pierre, 28 Jun 1941-5 Jul 1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    2 handwritten letters and a signed postcard. These letters deal with the importance of Grabbe's play "Scherz, Satire Ironie und tiefere Bedeutung."
  - Baskind, Jacques, 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    5 postcards.
  - Begot, Jean Pierre, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    2 handwritten letters, wants to borrow 291.
  - Bguin, Albert (Box 1, Folder 4)
    16 handwritten letters, 10 cards. While soliciting Bguin's advice about his translation of Grabbe, Valanay asks him to write a preface. Bguin turns him down and encourages Valanay to write the preface himself - which he eventually did. There is a discussion of literary magazines, Bguin's opinion of Valanay's poems Flot et jusant and Oiseau nitre, and Bguin supplies Valanay with information about Lichtenberg and Novalis.
  - Bhar, Henri (Box 1, Folder 4)
    1 typed letter, with minutes from Association pour l'tude du mouvement Dada.
  - Blias, Jean, 12 Oct 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    1 handwritten letter.
  - Bellmer, Hans, 30 Nov 1935 - 13 Nov 1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    31 handwritten letters. Many of the letters are written on pale pink paper and a few have a monogram - an H superimposed on a B - in the upper left-hand corner. A fair portion of the letters are undated but contents allow for an approximate reconstruction of their chronology. Joined: A photograph of the famous "poupe," 3 photograph-postcards presumable made by Bellmer, 6 invitations to Bellmer's exhibitions.
  - Berger, Pierre (See Prichard) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Berggruen, Henri, 22 Feb 1954, 23 Mar 1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    2 typed letters.
  - Bergman, Alfred, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    3 typed letters, 2 in German, one in French, concerning Valanay's translation of Grabbe.
  - Berkstein, Sonia, 6 Jan 1933 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Card in German.
  - Bern-Joffroy, Andr, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    2 handwritten letters and a typed letter 8 Jan 1974 on Affaires Culturelles letterhead.
  - Bertel, Ren, 15 Mar 1945-14 Jan 1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    3 handwritten letters and 5 typed letters. The letters concern the publication of Jacques Prvert's Paroles.
  - Bezzola, N., 1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    New Year's card.
  - Bibliographisches Institut AG, 5 Dec 1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Typed letter in German.
  - Billy, Andr, 1927, 1931, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    4 handwritten letters from 5 Feb 1927 to 30 Sep 1931 and a typed letter, undated.
  - Binet, Catherine, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Letters (1975), and an invitation from 1976.
  - Black, Jacob Nicole, 12 July 1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bobon, Daniel, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    2 typed letters, 7 Aug and 5 Apr 1965.
  - Boers, F., 8 Mar 1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bonmariage, Sylvain, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bonnard, S.C., 1932 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    2 handwritten letters, 18 May and 22 Jun 1932.
  - Borderie, Roger, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    2 handwritten letters 9 Aug and 2 Aug 1975 ask Valanay to correct some errors.
  - Benoit, Pierre, Andr, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    4 handwritten letters.
  - Bosmans, Andr (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Postcard.
  - Boucher, Maurice, 16 Aug 1921-30 Jan 1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    60 handwritten letters, 5 typed letters and 16 cards, the letters are relatively short. Boucher, a specialist in German literature and poet himself, seems to have been Valanay's teacher. The correspondence begins as a kind of mentor relationship with Boucher offering criticism and encouragement of Valanay's poetry and then changes to a cordial collegiality. The two men discuss the work, among others, of Stefan George, Lichtenberg, Mallarm and Hubert Eulenberg.
  - Boulen, Charles, 11 Oct 1928-12 Jun 1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    34 handwritten letters and 3 newspaper clippings. Boulen describes himself as the "pote cultivateur de Saint-Maclou-de-Folleville." As with Thret and Roinard, Boulen is an enthusiastic proponent of Norman poetry and much of the correspondence concerns the promotion and commemoration of his friends and colleagues. He also appreciates Valanay's poetic efforts, congratulating him on Flot et jusant.
  - Braque, M., 17 Nov 1930 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Breker, Arno, 23 Jan 1931-22 May 1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    12 handwritten letters and 12 postcards in French (many are undated). Breker discusses his projects with Valanay who had written a positive review of an early exhibition. Throughout the early thirties, they seem to be on very cordial terms. On the rare occasion when Breker does mention the political turmoil gripping Germany during this period, he says that he hopes "things will work themselves out."
  - Breton, Andr, 23 Feb 1923-24 Apr 1947 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    6 handwritten letters. Both a professional and cordial exchange between two poets who seem to share similar interests in art and politics.
  - Brun, Jean, 12 Aug 1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    3 letters and a carte-de-visite in which Brun refers to himself as "Professeur de Pataphysique." In the letters, Brun discusses his friend Bellmer, mentioning the latter's troubles, and solicits Valanay's assistance.
  - Brunius, Jacques, 28 Mar 1938, 27 Apr 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Brylinsky, Albert, 22 Dec 1942-19 Nov 1947 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Buf, Henry, 21 Oct 1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    1 typed letter in German.
  - Buffet-Picabia, Gabrielle, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Caumont, Jacques (Box 1, Folder 8)
    handwritten letters 4/26/1977.
  - Cendrars, Blaise, 7 Dec 1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    1 handwritten thank-you note on H. Matarasso stationary.
  - Char, Ren, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    1 handwritten letter: Char will miss a meeting with Valanay and apologizes.
  - Charon, A, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    1 handwritten letter: congratulations on Valanay's marriage.
  - Clarac-Serou, Max, 27 Dec 1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    1 typed letter.
  - Clarez, Maring, 9 Mar 1931 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Club Shell, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Cinquantenaire.
  - Coillot (Box 1, Folder 8)
    handwritten letters 10/19/1942.
  - Congrs International des Ecrivains Pour la Dfense de la Culture (Box 1, Folder 8)
    TLS 6/8/1935.
  - Copperie, Adrien, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    2 handwritten letters. Discussion of poems for Demain, Valanay is obviously a contributor.
  - Cournot, Michel, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Courter, P.J., 1 Feb 1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Couvert, Roger, 1973, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    2 letters..
  - Crotti, Jean, 28 Feb 1928-25 Mar 1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    4 handwritten letters. Affectionate letters in which Crotti thanks Valanay for an article the latter wrote; Crotti asks Valanay to collaborate on a project; Crotti sends condolence upon the death of Valanay's wife.
  - Deffoux, Leon, 25 Jun 1931 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Card.
  - Delaunay, Robert, 25 Jul 1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Demaison, Andr, 2 Nov 1929 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Divernois, Henri, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Divoire, Fernard, 9 Jun 1926 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    1 handwritten letter with letterhead from L'Intransigent.
  - Dollfus, Charles, 15 Feb 1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dorgels, Roland, 1 Jan 1931 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Doucet, Jacques (Box 1, Folder 8)
    "Etat des Priodiques de la Bibliothque Jacques Doucet."
  - Drouin, Ren, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    2 letters.
  - Du Flou, Maurice, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    3 handwritten letters. He is re-editing de Sade and Apollinaire and seeks Valanay's advice.
  - Duby, Henri, Louis, 24 Aug 1928 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - EDICORE, 4 Dec 1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    1 handwritten letter, signature unidentified.
  - Editions Pierre Belfond, 5 Apr 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Editions Gallimard, 21 Feb 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    1 typed letter. They turn down Valanay's offer for Unica Zurn's notebooks.
  - Editions Stendal et Cie, 29 Jul 1935 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    1 handwritten letter, signature is unidentified.
  - Eigenchenck, Athe, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    1 handwritten letter. A school teacher who solicits Valanay's thoughts on poetry and requests an autobiographical notice.
  - Elton, Arthur, 1950-1952, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    5 handwritten letters and a Christmas card.
  - Eluard, Paul, 3 Apr 1933-22 Jul 1942 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    25 handwritten letters. For the most part, this correspondence contains short messages and lettres pneumatiques concerning meetings, the purchase of books, translations, exchange of photographs and frequent mention of Eluard's declining health.
  - Ernst, Max, 16 Oct 1960-10 Apr 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    4 letters and 4 cards (two are of Ernst's paintings). Ernst attempts to supply Valanay with information on a Arcus Troll who was apparently associated with "Elf Scharfrichter." Discussion of a lithograph made by Ernst for Schwitter's "Auguste Bolte." Ernst expresses his annoyance at the behavior of a M. Belfond in relation to the publication of "Rire." With a translation of Christian Morgenstern's poem "Clture" by Ernst.
  - Etiemble, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Eulenberg, Herbert, 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    2 letters and 2 postcards in German. The letters concern Valanay's translation of Eulenberg's plays Alles um Geld and plans for a translation of Schattenbilder. With 3 letters from Eulenberg's son Till.
  - Fanido, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    1 handwritten letter and postcard.
  - Fauchois, Ren, 2 Jul 1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Fequet et Baudier, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    1 handwritten letter and 2 New Year's cards, including a wood-cut engraving by Arp.
  - Fret, Ch. Th., 1927-1929 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    10 handwritten letters (small aerograms). Fret, a poet from Normandy, discusses various questions concerning poetry with the young Valanay. It seems that they were introduced by Fernand Fleuret and share many mutual friends such as Napolon Roinard and Paul Eluard. Fret congratulates Valanay on a well written article.
  - Ferry, Jean, 1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    2 handwritten letters. Ferry thanks Valanay for making a gift to him of the latter's translation of Unica Zurn's memoirs and Kubin's work.
  - Feuillets Inutiles (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Invitation.
  - Filipacchi, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    1handwritten letter.
  - Fiumi, Lionello, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    1 handwritten letter. He received Valanay's Flot et Jusant and will write about it in the Italian press.
  - Flaire, V, de, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    1 letter and a postcard.
  - Fleuret, Fernand, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    8 letters and 5 postcards. A friendly correspondence that concerns mutual interests in the arts, mentions Billy, Apollinaire, Dufy, Fret and discusses Valanay's poems and translations.
  - Flouquet, Pierre Louis, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    3 postcards that concern Flouquet's journal and Valanay's offer to help distribute it.
  - Forster, L.W., 19 Nov 1932 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Frick, Louis de Gonzague, 6 Jan 1929-27 May 1934 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    24 handwritten letters and 9 postcards. Some are on letterhead: "La Bourgogne d'Or," "La Fort," "Lectures pour tous" and "Amis de 1914." In Frick's usual grandiloquent style, he congratulates and encourages Valanay's poetic efforts. He also reports on the lives and activities of his avant-garde friends.
  - Fuchs, 7 Jul 1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Gallimard, Librairie, 29 Dec 1934-5 Oct 1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    8 typed letters. Signed by Walter Mehring, Catherine von Blow, U. Karvelis and Catherine Gradwohl.
  - Gance, Abel, 16 Mar 1931 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    1 typed letter. Thanks Valanay for his positive review of Gance's books.
  - Gaspard, Jean, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Gaudfroy, M.H, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Giroud, Michel, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    2 letters. Publisher of Projectoire wants to publish something by Kurt Schwitters.
  - Glotz, Ren, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Goll, Iwan, 14 Jul 1930 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Gueigan, Bernard, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    1 handwritten letter. He would like to obtain the Apollinaire record.
  - Guer, A., 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Guillaume, Louis, 1965-1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    2 handwritten letters and 4 cards. With two poems "En Trois Coups d'Aile" and "Noir Comme La Mer."
  - Harivel, John, Le, 1964-1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Letters. Harivel also worked for Shell and the two men seem to have shared a close relationship - Harivel uses the "tu" form of address when writing to Valanay. Harivel sometimes signs his letters either "Jean" or "le petit Jerry."
  - Harrossowitz, Otto, 2 Apr 1941 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Hausmann, Herta, 11 Feb 1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    1 handwritten letter concerning the death of Bellmer.
  - Hausmann, Raoul, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    4 handwritten lettersasking if Valanay would do a final revision of his Courrier Dada. Valanay eventually declines. With a typed manuscript of "Synthetisches Cine der Malerei" dated 1918.
  - Heine, Maurice, 1934-1938 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    9 handwritten letters. Heine, one of the founding editors of Minotaure, complains to Valanay about the amount of time that the publication demands. He is also working on an edition of Sade's 120 Days. A few of the letters deal with arranging a meeting between the two men.
  - Henry, Ruth, ca. 1968-1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    16 letters, 10 cards and telegram - most are undated. Most of the letters are written in extreme haste asking for Valanay's advice on questions of translation or finding a particular citation. Valanay and Ruth collaborated on various translations.
  - Herboulot, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Huelsenbeck, Richard, 1949-1953 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    10 letters in German. With 2 letters from Beate Huelsenbeck.
  - Hugnet, Georges, 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    8 handwritten letters and 4 postcards. An intimate and friendly correspondence, Hugnet solicits Valanay's contribution of poetry and translation for Contre-Attaque, a journal that he edits. Hugnet alludes to the difficulties of living in occupied Paris and expresses his concern about Max Ernst who, as a German citizen, was interned and prosecuted by the Gestapo.
  - Hugues, Jean, 1965, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    3 letters.
  - Hyde, Jacqueline, 27 Nov 1973 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Institute for the Arts, Rice University, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    1 letter.
  - Kerr, Bobby, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Jacob, Black, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Jaguer, Edouard, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)